I realized the other day I've been
teaching stuff for 10 years. I was a
voice coach for 6 years and I've been
doing this job teaching devs for 4
years. And for a while I've been
thinking, wouldn't it be great if I
could take everything I know about
teaching and put it inside a skill so
that anyone could learn anything. I had
a long bus ride to London the other day
and I wrote a teach skill and it turns
out that it's pretty good. It taught me
how to solve a Rubik's cube, which is
something, you know, I've always wanted
to learn how to do, but I'd never really
had the time or inclination to do it.
But with this teach skill, it felt like
I had a real teacher who was teaching
how I like to be taught and was totally
aligned with my mission. And I'm going
to show you how I did it. The key
concept when we're looking at a teach
skill is some skills can be stateful and
some skills can be stateless. If a skill
is stateless, it means that it doesn't
retain any state from previous runs. it
doesn't have any memory of the things
that you've done before. In other words,
a stateless skill doesn't save anything
on the file system to help it pick up
where it left off later. Whereas
stateful skills do do that. They save
things either to the local file system
or they save things to MCP servers. They
keep notes that they later track.
Initially, I was thinking about teach as
a kind of stateless skill where you
would just say, "Teach me this thing."
and then it would just find some good
resources for you and give you like a an
output that would teach you a lesson
about that thing. But I realized that
all the good teaching that I do is
stateful where I teach you. I being the
teacher, I remember where you've got to.
I know what you've learned. I know what
you can go to next. And I've got a bunch
of great resources that I remember from
previous times that I've taught this
thing to teach you about it. So I
decided that teach had to be a stateful
skill. As an example, if you've used my
skills repo before, you know that grill
me is totally stateless. It just grills
you about a topic until you're ready to
implement. But then grill with docs is
actually stateful. In other words, it
saves some local ADRs, architectural
decision records. It saves some other
stuff, some uh glosseries to the repo as
well. And so Grill with docs is stateful
and it gets better over time, whereas
grill me is totally stateless. Now, one
of these is not better than the other.
They're just useful in different
situations. And so when you're designing
skills, you need to be careful to think
about whether they need to be stateless
or stateful. And teach needed to be
stateful. The way you install this skill
is you go to my skills repo
mapper.kills. You go down to this quick
start here and you just run the
skills.sh installer and you choose the
teach skill. Once you do that, you go to
an empty directory and you run teach
inside your coding agent. So for
instance in this directory which is my
Rubik's cube directory I said teach me
to how to solve a Rubik's cube. And
you'll notice during my journey how many
files it has created here. But the first
one it created was the mission. I
believe that for a teacher to be
effective you need to understand why a
student wants to learn the thing. And so
I got this skill to create a mission for
you. Here it says Matt wants to be able
to take a scramble 3x3 Rubik's cube and
solve it unaded at least once. The goal
is the achievement itself, not speed,
not theory. The next thing it does is it
creates a set of resources. So, it goes
and searches the web for actual primary
source highrust resources that it's
going to use to create the lessons out
of. It does this on the first pass when
you ask it to teach you something and
then it will continue to update these as
you go and then it will create your
first lesson for you. And lessons are
stored in the lessons folder and they're
numbered like this and they're all
individual HTML files. HTML is just so
much richer than markdown. It allows it
to be so much more expressive, so much
more interactive. And this is really the
core of what makes this such a good
learning experience. And here is my
first lesson, anatomy, notation, and the
white cross. And it basically teaches
you just what you need to know at that
moment. It gives you diagrams, gives you
very simple explainers, gives you call
outs, and it gives you quizzes, too. One
thing I find really important whenever
you're teaching anything is to develop a
feedback loop. And quizzes are okay at
this. They're basically good if you
can't find any richer feedback loop.
Again, if we zoom down this, we've got
notations, we've got traps, we've got
your first skill here. And so, it's
giving me the knowledge that I need, but
also encouraging me to develop the
skills I need, which is slightly
different. And the and the skill itself
knows that. Once I completed the lesson
and I said, "Yes, I can make the white
cross," then it recommended that or
rather recorded that inside a learning
record here. And these learning records
are very simple records that the agent
creates when I report how I'm doing. So
this allows it to keep track of how I'm
doing and just like a real teacher then
tailor the next lesson to what I need.
Here's another explainer from slightly
further down this course. I suppose it's
kind of creating a course as we go based
on what I need. So this one here it was
okay. It started to add like little
citations now. Again, more quizzes. I
mean, I I just find this layout really
nice to look at and really useful. I was
sort of working on the skill as I was
building this to and so I added this
little bottom or thing at the bottom. It
says it tries to find uh communities
where you can ask questions here because
sure you can develop knowledge and
skills here, but the only way you're
going to be develop wisdom about the
thing is actually interacting with a
community, testing your ideas out in the
real world. It also develops reference
material for you, too. This was
something I noticed that I needed. So
there's a glossery. This glossery has
the anatomy. It has the notation here.
It has the solving grip, the daisy. Sort
of anything like weird jargon that we've
learned is going to go into the
glossery. This is really useful,
especially if you're learning like a
coding language using this. It also
means that future lessons can be more
concise because they're able to
reference the term in the glossery and
you can look back if you're confused. It
also creates cheat sheets for you. So
this is a solve card here where it's
basically just giving me the entire
solve. If I want just a single place to
look at how to create or solve a Rubik's
cube, this is the place I can go. And
finally, just to explain this notes.md
file, this is where the agent can note
down any of my preferences, note down
any watch outs, and it's just kind of
internal note-taking for the agent
itself. So let's imagine that I sit down
to a session and I basically want to
fill in the teacher on what I've been
doing since I last had a session. So, I
just say teach and I can basically
complete the Rubik's cube now except for
the corner cycle which I've still not
quite got into memory. Let's go ahead
and see what it says. It starts, of
course, because this is an empty context
by checking the state of my teaching
workspace. It's checking all of the
solve cards, seeing how far I've got to.
It's now giving me a decent diagnosis
for what I'm feeling. It's saying the
concept is solid for the corner cycle,
which is a particular al algorithm, but
it's the one that hasn't reached muscle
memory. Let me look at the existing
memorization lesson and one earlier
lesson to match the house style. So,
we've turned the agent basically into a
teacher, and you've got to work with it
in the same way that you would any
one-to-one teacher. You tell it what
problems you're having, and it will
design lessons to find solutions. The
model I'm using here is Opus 4.8 with
medium effort. By the way, it's also
using a key teaching term here. The zone
of proximal development, one algorithm,
pure muscle memory work. The zone of
proximal development is this key
teaching idea which I am obsessed with.
And it's the idea that you should always
teach someone in the area where they are
perfectly challenged but not
intimidated. This means that every
lesson has to be concise, compact, and
exactly framed at that zone of proximal
development. So the students not bored
but also not freaked out. So we can see
it's now created this lesson, the corner
cycle lesson, and it's created this
exact lesson for us. So it's basically
just breaking it down, paying more
attention to it, giving me new mental
models. One four move phrase played
twice. Okay, that is handy. And the idea
is I would walk through this lesson. Oh,
look at this. Oh my gosh, look at this.
So it's actually given me an interactive
tap thing I could do. Okay. So, it's U R
U prime L prime U RP prime U prime L. Oh
my god, look at this. So, it's got
guided mode. So, I can turn off that.
Oh, that's that's unreasonably cool. You
see what being in HTML gives us here,
right? We've got the full power of the
browser to mess about with here. So, you
get the idea of what these lessons look
like. They are short. They are really
focused. And it gives me exactly what to
practice now. And this also means
because everything has been saved to the
file system, I can clear this and every
time I run teach again, it will have all
the context it needs to keep me in the
zone of proximal development. Let's
briefly look at the skill itself here.
It's really quite simple, although it is
one of the longer skills that I've put
together. The user has asked you to
teach them something. This is a stateful
request. They intend to learn the topic
over multiple sessions. It goes into the
shape of the teaching workspace, which
we've looked at already, and it has a
sectional philosophy here. So I really
define the terms that the AI should
think in. It should think in terms of
giving them knowledge from highquality
high trust resources, skills, highly
relevant interactive lessons and
actually developing the skills and then
wisdom that comes from interacting from
other learners and practitioners. We go
further down here and we touch on the
shape of the lessons themselves. We've
talked about the mission as well.
mission.mmd the zone of proximal
development acquiring knowledge and
skills how to do that acquiring wisdom
which basically when the learner is
ready to go out into the world once
they've got the knowledge and skills how
do you delegate them to the community
when the user asks a question that
appears to require wisdom your default
posture should be to attempt to answer
but to ultimately delegate to a
community my idea with this teach skill
is not to have you hooked onto the agent
for learning everything it's to actually
give you the skills you need to feel
confident to go out and work with a
community and send you out into the
world. That's the dream of this stuff.
We've also got more material here on
reference documents, then finally on
notes.md. But that really is the skill.
There's a few little bits of supporting
documents for like learning record
format, the mission format, the
resources format, etc. In terms of
engineering, I can imagine this skill
being really useful in onboarding people
to a codebase. Creating documentation is
a real pain in the ass because not only
do you need to keep it up to date, but
that documentation is probably outside
the person's zone of proximal
development. They might have worked with
your stack before, they might just need
to know the specific problem domain or
they might have worked with the problem
domain before, but they have no idea
what TypeScript is or things like that.
So, you can think of teach here as, you
know, you start them off in their own
workspace. You point them at the
codebase. You teach them how to, you
know, they learn independently how to
work with the code, what the concepts
are, and guess what? You've got a
productive employee in record time. For
me, I'm excited to use this just on my
side projects, on having fun, on just
learning stuff that I wouldn't have
learned how to do before. You know,
solving this freaking Rubik's cube. I
might even dig out a bit of old chess
material and see if it can teach me some
openings. And I wanted to end here by
talking about an idea that I've had for
a while that I think this teach skill
really proves or rather makes very plain
to me which is that we the developer
community engineers out there are the
first people to really experience what
AI can do on something that it's really
good at. AI is currently better at
writing code than it is at almost
anything else. There are a few
exceptions, but really AI is very good
at writing code and developers have an
advantage that we're the first people to
really get to test AI out on a problem
where it's very good at it. This means
that we are the first people really in
the world, you know, with a couple of
exceptions that get to know AI, that get
to build these cool things. And it means
that we're the first movers in this new
space. we can take the ideas that we
develop here, turn them into skills and
start bringing them out to the world. I
think that's incredibly exciting and
it's something that I'm going to be
exploring more. And this teach skill is
kind of the first phase of that. So when
you're working with claw code or codeex
and you're struggling with it and you're
losing motivation, you think, "God, this
sucks." Just think that you'll be able
to take the skills that you are learning
now, the instincts that you're building
working with AI and take them outside of
coding domains. that I think is going to
be an incredibly valuable skill no
matter what the future of work looks
like. We're all going to be working with
AI and we are the first people to really
get to do it. Now, if you're digging my
skills, then you should go to AI
hero/skills
and sign up for my newsletter that lets
you know whenever I release a new skill,
whenever I have any changes because I do
change the skills all the time. If you
want up-to-date information on how to
use my skills for engineering and for
other stuff, too, then check it out. But
overall, thanks for watching. I can't
wait to see the languages that you're
learning, coding languages or human
languages, the new skills that you're
developing. I'm going to get this thing
to teach me vocal harmonies as well.
It's always a skill that I've wanted to
know but never been very good at. And I
just can't wait to get using this thing
myself and seeing how you're using it,
too. But overall, thanks so much for
watching and I will see you very